SARANSH CHOPRA

🕏 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🗷 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🛅 saransh-cpp | 🗘 Saransh-cpp | 📢 WhiteViolin

About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains open-source research software, which he believes are the key to collaborative and reproducible research.

He is passionate about Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Research Software.

Education

Cluster Innovation Centre, University of Delhi

New Delhi, India

Major: Information Technology and Mathematical Innovations

2020 - 2024

 $Minor:\ Computational\ Biology$

CGPA 9.46

Research and Work Experience

FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Open-source developer and technical writer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language]

May 2022 - Present

Mr. Dhairya Gandhi (Julia Computing)

- Fixing bugs and developing the infrastructure of prominent Julia ML and DL libraries such as Flux.jl (3,700+ stars), NNlib.jl (Neural Network primitives 150+ stars), Metalhead.jl (Computer vision models 270+ stars), and Functors.jl.
- Writing original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.
- Working closely with doctoral researchers and FluxML maintainers from around the world.

Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics (IRIS-HEP), Princeton University

Remote

IRIS-HEP research fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

June 2022 - September 2022

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University)

- Prepared Vector (72,000+ installs 40+ stars) for v0.9.0, v0.10.0, and v1.0.0 (first major release) by developing new public API, fixing bugs, and building new infrastructure.
- The releases are currently being used by researchers at CERN, ATLAS, CMS, and Princeton University to construct 4D jagged (awkward) vectors and perform Just-In-Time compiled vector operations in Python.
- Worked closely with CERN and Princeton researchers to build infrastructures for the HEP ecosystem.

AiView New Delhi, India

Research and development enginner

September 2021 - December 2021

Mr. Geetansh Saxena and Mr. Chappa Sri Vinay

- Developed end-to-end OCR and Object Detection libraries by wrapping the existing technologies for visually impaired people.
- Built a CI/CD pipeline and a REST API for ease of integration with any existing software using FastAPI and Heroku.
- o Collected a dataset of human images and their distance from a point by building a stereovision camera.

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling), NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code student developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 - August 2021

Prof. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick), Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command, created a CI/CD pipeline, and followed a micro-services-based architecture.
- Worked closely with post-doctoral research fellows and PyBaMM maintainers from around the world.

Publications

[Tra+21] T. G. Tranter, R. Timms, V. Sulzer, F. B. Planella, G. M. Wiggins, S. V. Karra, P. Agarwal, S. Chopra, S. Allu, P. R. Shearing, and D. J. L. Brett. *liionpack: A Python package for simulating packs of batteries with PyBaMM*. Journal of Open Source Software, 7(70), 4051. Oct. 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.04051.

Open Source Research Software

PyBaMM

Maintainer and Core Developer - 215,000+ installs - 420+ stars

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

Vector

Maintainer and Core Developer - 72,000+ installs - 40+ stars

Vector is a Python 3.6+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics problems in a NumPy-like way.

[SSP] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Vector: vector classes and utilities. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.5942082. URL: https://github.com/scikit-hep/vector.

Flux.jl

Member and Core Contributor - 80,000+ installs - 3,700+ stars

Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

BattBot

Maintainer and Core Developer - 130+ followers - 10+ stars

An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested Battery Simulations.

liionpack

Maintainer and Core Developer - 2,000+ installs - 30+ stars

liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

Other notable contributions

- DeepXDE: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 330,000+ installs 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential equations using Physics-Informed neural networks.
- Colour: Colour Science for Python 6,000,000+ installs 1,500+ stars Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces.
- Scikit-HEP ecosystem: High Energy Physics in Python
 Fixed minor bugs in awkward and hist, added support for coverage in cookie, and wrote new developer pages.

Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research (ACAT). Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] **S. Chopra**, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector. 5th International Workshop on Python in High-Energy-Physics (PyHEP). Presentation. Oct. 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7067310. URL: https://indi.to/bPmMc.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Python packaging: from stone age to the future. PyDelhi workshop. Presentation. Sept. 2022.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 10th Annual Conference on Python Asia-Pacific (PyCon APAC). Presentation. Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22c] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 21st Annual Conference On Python Europe (EuroPython). Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.
- [S C22d] S. Chopra. Vector Constructors, documentation, and benchmarks. IRIS-HEP Lightning Talks. Presentation. June 2022. URL: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fLt7BHuASpw.
- [S C21] S. Chopra. BattBot: Mathematical Modeling of Batteries using an automated Twitter bot. 1st International Training Workshop on Python Battery Mathematical Modeling (PyBaMM). Presentation. Oct. 2021. URL: https://www.pybamm.org/training.

Grants, Prizes and Achievements

o PyCon Acia-Pacific (APAC)'s grant to lead a talk virtually (NT\$3,600)	July 2022
\circ Shubhra Kar Linux Foundation Training Scholarship (500 recipients worldwide) for contributions to open-source research software (\$695)	June 2022
\circ Euro Python's travel grant to lead a talk in-person (£460)	June~2022
\circ PyCon Italia's travel grant to lead a workshop in-person (£400 + lodging support)	$April\ 2022$
\circ Faraday Institution's Collaboration Award for contributions to the PyBaMM ecosystem	$November\ 2021$
\circ Won the Elastic hackathon (out of 2500+ registrations) with a Flutter-Node-Google Cloud	$May\ 2021$

 \circ Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data Pan-STARRS August 2016 observatory

Projects

releaseup [NLP, Summarisation, spaCy, Scikit-learn, TF-IDF, Python library]

September 2022

- Releaseup uses an extractive approach for generating release notes from comments and docstrings added between two git tags.
- The Python library has 10+ installs on PyPI, 5+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

OCRed [OCR, Computer Vision, Tesseract-OCR, NLTK, Python library]

August 2022

- OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 1,400+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente [NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions]

June 2022

- Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

ChaoticEncryption.jl [Image processing, Encryption algorithms, ODEs, PRNGs, Julia package]

February 2022

- Vectorised image encryption and PRNG algorithms that runs ~40X faster than ordinary nested-for implementations.
- The Julia package has 10+ installs on JuliaHub and 25+ stars on GitHub.

PDEsWithPINNs [PDEs, PINNs, Python, DeepXDE]

based ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) application

January 2022

- Worked under Prof. Shobha Bagai to solve 1, 2, 3, and 4D Partial Differential Equations using Physics-Informed Neural Networks.
- Worked with Neural tangent Kernels, Multi-scale Fourier feature networks, and Spatio-temporal Multi-scale Fourier feature networks to predict high-frequency details.

SceneNet [Transfer Learning, VGG19, CNNs, Python, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Heroku]

December 202.

- Scenery detection through an Android application by training VGG-19 on 10,000+ images belonging to 67 categories.
- Achieved 96% training accuracy, 64% cross-validation accuracy, and developed a standalone public API for the model.

Volunteering

PyHEP Hackashop 2022

September 2022

 Collaborated with High Energy Physics researchers to organise a hackathon+workshop (hackashop) for Python's High Energy Physics ecosystem.

Google Summer of Code

May - September 2022

 Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS, on projects involving, but not limited to, documentation, DevOps, parameterisation, and visualization.

CodePeak December 2021

• Mentored 10+ students in the field of open-source application development.

Relevant Skills

Languages:	Julia Python C/C++ Java JavaScript Dart
Frameworks/Libraries:	Tensorflow PyTorch spaCy NLTK Tesseract-OCR FluxML-Ecosystem DeepXDE PyData-Ecosystem SciML-Ecosystem Flutter FastAPI NodeJS
Platforms and Tools	Linux Android Heroku Google Cloud Elasticsearch Kibana Firebase Docker CI/CD
Research Interests:	Deep Learning Machine Learning Scientific ML OSS Research Software

Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (basic), Punjabi (conversational)